Well, this is 2009.
حسناً, انه عام ال(2009)
And it's the Bicentenary of Charles Darwin.
حيث يصادف المئوية الثانية ل(تشارلز داروين)
And all over the world, eminent evolutionists
و العالم بأسره, بالتطور البارز الذي توصل له
are anxious to celebrate this.
يتوق للاحتفال بهذه المناسبة
And what they're planning to do is to enlighten us
عبر تنويرنا
on almost every aspect
بمعظم جوانب المختلفة
of Darwin and his life,
عن داروين و حياته
and how he changed our thinking.
و كيف بدل طريقة تفكيرنا
I say almost every aspect,
و انا اقول معظم النواحي
because there is one aspect of this story
لأن هناك جانب من هذه القصة
which they have thrown no light on.
لم يلقوا عليه الضوء
And they seem anxious to skirt around it and step over it
و يبدو انهم حريصين على أن يتجنبوا هذا الموضوع
and to talk about something else.
و يتحدثوا عن شيء اخر
So I'm going to talk about it.
لذا سأتحدث انا عنه
It's the question of, why are we so different from the chimpanzees?
و هو السؤال التالي: لماذا نحن مختلفون جداً عن الشامبانزي؟
We get the geneticists keeping on telling us
دائما نسمع علماء الجينات يحدثونّا
how extremely closely we are related -- hardly any genes of difference,
عن كم نحن شديدي الارتباط, حيث انه صعب العثور على جينات مختلفة
very, very closely related.
مرتبطين جداً جداً
And yet, when you look at the phenotypes,
و حتى عند النظر الى التنوع السموي
there's a chimp, there's a man;
هذا شمبانزي, و هذا انسان
they're astoundingly different,
انهما مختلفان بشكل كبير
no resemblance at all.
لا تشابه على الاطلاق
I'm not talking about airy-fairy stuff
و انا لا اتحدث امور خيالية هنا
about culture or psychology, or behavior.
عن الثقافة, او علم النفس, او السلوك
I'm talking about ground-base, nitty-gritty,
انا اتحدث عن امور اساسية, جوهرية
measurable physical differences.
امور ملموسة, قابلة للقياس
They, that one,
اليكم هذا المثال
is hairy and walking on four legs.
هذا ذو شعر كثيف, و يمشي على اربعة اطراف
That one is a naked biped. Why?
و ذاك عاري الجسم و يمشي على قدمين, لماذ؟
I mean --
اعني...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
if I'm a good Darwinist, I've got to believe
اذا كنت داروني جيد , علي الاعتقاد
there's a reason for that.
ان هناك سبب لذلك
If we changed so much, something must have happened.
اذا كنّا قد تغيرنا كثيرا, اذن هناك شيء ما حدث
What happened?
ما الذي حدث؟
Now 50 years ago, that was a laughably simple question.
منذ 50 عاما كان هذا سؤال بسيط مضحك
Everybody knew the answer.
و كان الجميع يعرف اجابته
They knew what happened.
و كانو يعرفون ما حصل
The ancestor of the apes stayed in the trees;
ظل جدود القرود على الاشجار
our ancestors went out onto the plain.
اما جدودنا فقد نزلوا الى الارض
That explained everything.
و هذا يفسر كل شيء
We had to get up on our legs to peer over the tall grass,
كان علينا الوقوف على ارجلنا لنرى ما يختبيء بين الحشائش الطويلة
or to chase after animals,
او لمطاردة حيوانات اخرى
or to free our hands for weapons.
او لنطلق ايدينا لاستخدام الاسلحة
And we got so overheated in the chase
و قد حمينا جداً خلال المطاردات
that we had to take off that fur coat and throw it away.
لذا خلعنا الغطاء الفرو و تخلصنا منه
Everybody knew that, for generations.
الجميع عرف ذلك, لاجيال
But then, in the '90s, something began to unravel.
و لكن في التسعنييات أمور قد بدأت تتكشف
The paleontologists themselves looked a bit more closely
حيث بدأ علماء الحفريات بأنفسهم اعادة النظر بتمعن
at the accompanying microfauna
على الحيوانات المرافقة الدقيقة
that lived in the same time and place as the hominids.
التي عاشت في نفس المكان والزمان الذي عاش به الانسان
And they weren't savanna species.
و التي لم تكن من انواع السافاننا
And they looked at the herbivores. And they weren't savanna herbivores.
و راقبوا العواشب, و لم تكن من عواشب السافننا
And then they were so clever, they found a way to analyze
و كانو شديدي الذكاء حيث انهم قد وجدوا طريقه للتحليل
fossilized pollen.
احافير غبار الطلع
Shock, horror.
الصدمة و الرعب
The fossilized pollen was not of savanna vegetation.
انها لم تكن من اشجار السافننا
Some of it even came from lianas,
حتى ان بعضها اتى من ليناس
those things that dangle in the middle of the jungle.
هذه الشياء التي تتدلى في وسط الغابة
So we're left with a situation where
نحن نحن الان في موقف حيث اننا
we know that our earliest ancestors
نعرف أن اسلافنا البدائين
were moving around on four legs in the trees,
تنقلوا على (قدمين) في الاشجار
before the savanna ecosystem even came into existence.
حتى قبل ظهور نظام السافننا الايكولوجي على الوجود
This is not something I've made up.
و هذا ليس من تلفيقي
It's not a minority theory.
و ليست نظربة الاقلية
Everybody agrees with it.
فالكل يتفق معها
Professor Tobias came over from South Africa
حيث جاء البروفيسور توبياس من امريكا الجنوبية
and spoke to University College London.
و تحدث في جامعة لندن
He said, "Everything I've been telling you for the last 20 years,
وقال: كل ما اقوله لكم منذ 20 عاما الماضية
forget about it. It was wrong.
انسوه, فهو خاطيء
We've got to go back to square one and start again."
علينا الرجوع الى نقطة البداية, و البدء من جديد
It made him very unpopular. They didn't want to go back to square one.
و ذلك قلل من شعبيته . لم يرغب الناس في العودة الى نقطة البداية
I mean, it's a terrible thing to happen.
اعني, انه شيء فظيع
You've got this beautiful paradigm.
كنت قد حصلت على نموذج جميل
You've believed it through generations.
و امنت به عبر مر الاجيال
Nobody has questioned it.
و لم يشكك به احد
You've been constructing fanciful things on top of it,
و بنيت اشياء خيالية على ذلك
relying on it to be as solid as a rock.
معتمدين على صحة النظرية و صلابتها
And now it's whipped away from under you.
و الان قد سُحبت منك
What do you do? What does a scientist do in that case?
ماذا تغعل؟ مذا يفعل العلماء في تلك الحالة
Well, we know the answer because
حسناً, جميعنا يعرف الاجابة لان
Thomas S. Kuhn
توماس س كوهن
wrote a seminal treatise
كتب اطروحة التطور
about this back in 1962.
و عن هذا لنعود الى 1962
He said what scientists do
حيث قال: ما يفعله العلماء
when a paradigm fails
عندما يفشل نموذج
is, guess what -- they carry on as if nothing had happened.
هو, احزروا ماذا, يتابعون العمل كأن شيئا لم يحدث
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If they haven't got a paradigm they can't ask the question.
ان لم يكن لديهم نموذج, لا يستطيعون طرح الاسئلة
So they say, "Yes it's wrong,
لذا يقولون:" نعم انه خاطيء
but supposing it was right ..."
و لكن على فرض انه صحيح ..."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the only other option open to them
و الخيار الوحيد المتاح لهم
is to stop asking the questions.
التوقف عن طرح الاسئلة
So that is what they have done now.
و ذلك ما فعلوه الان
That's why you don't hear them talking about it. It's yesterday's question.
و لهذا لا تسمعهم يتحدثون عنه. انه سؤال الامس
Some of them have even elevated it into a principle.
بعضهم رفع النظرية لتصبح مبدأ
It's what we ought to be doing.
هذا ما يتعين علينا القيام به.
Aaron Filler from Harvard said,
وقال ارون فيلير من جامعة هارفارد ،
"Isn't it time we stopped talking about selective pressures?
ألم يحن الوقت بعد لتوقف عن الحديث عن ضغوطات انتقائية؟
I mean, why don't we talk about, well, there's chromosomes, and there's genes.
اعني لماذا لا نتحدث عنها, الكروموسومات موجودة, و الجينات موجودة ايضاً
And we just record what we see."
و نسجل ما نراه فقط"
Charles Darwin must be spinning in his grave!
لا بد من ان تشارلز دارزين يتقلب في قبره الان !
He knew all about that kind of science.
فقد كان يعلم كل ما يتعلق بهذا العلم
And he called it hypothesis-free science.
و كان يدعوه بعلم الفرضية الحرة
And he despised it from the bottom of his heart.
و كان يزدريها من اعماق قلبه
And if you're going to say,
و اذا اردنا القول:
"I'm going to stop talking about selective pressures,"
"سأتوقف عن الحديث عن موضوعات انتقائية
you can take "The Origin of Species" and throw it out of the window,
اذاً عليك ان تلقي بنظرية "اصل الانواع" من النافذة
for it's about nothing else but selective pressures.
لأنها لا تتحدث سوى عن موضوعات انتقائية
And the irony of it is,
والمثير للسخرية ان
that this is one occasion of a paradigm collapse
هذا احد اسباب انهيار هذا النموذج
where we didn't have to wait for a new paradigm to come up.
حيث لم نكن بحاجة لانتظار ظهور نموذج جديد
There was one waiting in the wings.
فقد كان واحد على اهبة الاستعداد
It had been waiting there since 1960
كان ينتظر منذ عام 1960
when Alister Hardy, a marine biologist,
عندما الستر هاردي، عالم الاحياء البحري
said, "I think what happened,
قال:"اظن ان ما حدث
perhaps our ancestors
ان اسلافنا ربما
had a more aquatic existence
عاشو حياة مائية اكثر
for some of the time."
لبعض من الوقت"
He kept it to himself for 30 years.
و ابقى هذه الفرضية لنفسه 30 عاما
But then the press got hold of it and all hell broke loose.
ولكن بعد ذلك حصلت عليه الصحافة ، و انفتحت ابواب الجحيم.
All his colleagues said, "This is outrageous.
و قال زملاؤه "هذا امر مهين
You've exposed us to public ridicule!
لقد عرضتنا لسخرية الجميع
You must never do that again."
يجب ان لا تفعل ذلك ثانيةً"
And at that time, it became set in stone:
ومنذ ذلك الوقت اصبحت النظرية
the aquatic theory should be dumped
النظرية المائية يجب التخلص منها
with the UFOs and the yetis,
مع هذه الاجسام الغريبة و الغيلان
as part of the lunatic fringe of science.
بعيداً عن الجماعات العلمية المتطرفة
Well I don't think that.
حسناً، انا لا اظن ذلك
I think that Hardy had a lot going for him.
و اعتقد انه كان لدى هاردي الكثير
I'd like to talk about just a handful
و اود الحديث عن القليل
of what have been called the
عما كان يطلق عليه
hallmarks of mankind,
البصمات البشرية
the things that made us different from everybody else,
الشيء الذي ميزنا عن غيرنا
and all our relatives.
و عن جميع اقربائنا
Let's look at our naked skin.
لنلقي نظرة على جلدنا العاري
It's obvious that most of the things we think about
من الواضح ان معظم الامور التي نفكر بها
that have lost their body hair, mammals without body hair,
لقد فقدوا شعر جسمهم، الثديات بلا شعر على الجسم
are aquatic ones, like the dugong, the walrus,
هي ثديات مائية، مثل الاطوم، والفظ
the dolphin, the hippopotamus, the manatee.
و الدلفين، فرس النهر ، وخروف ا لبحر
And a couple of wallowers-in-mud like the babirusa.
و نوعين من الحيوانات التي تتمرغ في الطين، مثل الخنزير البري
And you're tempted to think, well perhaps,
و قد تميل للتفكير، انه ربما
could that be why we are naked?
السبب في كوننا عراة الجسم
I suggested it and people said, "No no no.
لقد اقترحت انا ذلك، ولكن الناس رفضوا ذلك
I mean, look at the elephant.
ما عنيه، انظروا الى الفيلة
You've forgotten all about the elephant haven't you?"
نسيتوا كل ما يتعلق بالفيلة، اليس كذلك؟
So back in 1982 I said,
لذا عودة الى 1982، حين قلت
"Well perhaps the elephant had an aquatic ancestor."
"ربما قد كان للفيلة اسلاف مائية"
Peals of merry laughter!
دوي من الضحكات!
"That crazy woman. She's off again. She'll say anything won't she?"
"هذه العجوز خرفت مجدداً، ستقول اي شيء في بالها ، اليس كذلك؟"
But by now, everybody agrees that the elephant had an aquatic ancestor.
و لكن في هذا الوقت الجميع اتفق على وجود اسلاف مائية للفيلة.
This has come 'round to be that all those naked pachyderms
و هذا ما جعل الفيلة حيوانات عارية
have aquatic ancestors.
وجود الاسلاف المائية
The last exception was supposed to be the rhinoceros.
و الاستثناء الاخير هو حيوان وحيد القرن
Last year in Florida they found extinct ancestor of a rhinoceros
في العام الماضي وجد في ولاية فلوريدا سلف حيوان وحيد القرن المنقرض
and said, "Seems to have spent most of its time in the water."
و قيل" يبدو انه قضى معظم حياته في الماء"
So this is a close connection between nakedness and water.
وهذا دليل على الصلة الوثيقة بين الخلو من الشعر و الماء
As an absolute connection, it only works one way.
علاقة اكيدة، تعمل بطريقة واحدة
You can't say all aquatic animals are naked,
لا يمكن القول ان جميع الحيوانات المائية عارية
because look at the sea otter.
انظر الى ثعلب الماء
But you can say
و لكن يمكن القول
that every animal that has become naked
ان كل حيوان اصبح عارياً
has been conditioned by water, in its own lifetime,
قد تكيف مع الماء في فترة حياته
or the lifetime of its ancestors. I think this is significant.
او في في فترة حياة اسلافهم. اظن ان هذا شيء هام
The only exception is the naked Somalian mole-rat,
الخلد الصومالي الحالة الاستثنائية الوحيدة
which never puts its nose above the surface of the ground.
الذي لا يخرج فوق الارض
And take bipedality.
و يتجول فيها على قدمين
Here you can't find anybody to compare it with,
في هذه الحالة لا يوجد حيوان اخر ليقارن به
because we're the only animal that walks upright on two legs.
لاننا الحيوانات الوحيدة التي تمشي على قدمين
But you can say this: all the apes and all the monkeys
و لكن يمكن القول ان جميع القرود
are capable of walking on two legs,
باستطاعتها المشي على اثنتين
if they want to, for a short time.
ان ارادت، لكن لمده قصيرة
There is only one circumstance in which they
هناك حالة وحيدة فيها
always, all of them, walk on two legs,
عادة جميعهم يمشون على اثنتين
and that is when they are wading through water.
و ذلك عندما يعبرون الماء
Do you think that's significant?
هل تظنون ان لهذا اهمية؟
David Attenborough thinks it's significant,
ديفيد أتينبورو يعتقد ذلك
as the possible beginning of our bipedalism.
على انها البداية للمشي على قدمين
Look at the fat layer.
انظروا الى طبقة الشحوم
We have got, under our skin, a layer of fat, all over:
الموجودة تحت جلدنا، الاطبقة موجودة في جميع انحاء جسمنا
nothing in the least like that in any other primate.
لا شيء اقل منه في اي من الرئيسيات
Why should it be there?
ما سبب وجودها؟
Well they do know, that if you look at other aquatic mammals,
انهم يعلمون انه اذا نظرت الى الثديات المائية الاخرى
the fat that in most land mammals
الشحوم موجودة عند معظم الثديات البرية
is deposited inside the body wall,
يتم تخزينها داخل الجسم
around the kidneys and the intestines and so on,
حول الكلى و الامعاء و ما الى ذلك
has started to migrate to the outside,
بدات بالخروج الى الخارج
and spread out in a layer inside the skin.
و الانتشار في طبقات تحت الجلد
In the whale it's complete:
و قد تم ذلك في الحيتان
no fat inside at all, all in blubber outside.
لا وجود للشحوم في الداخل، كله في الجلد الخارجي
We cannot avoid the suspicion
و نحن لا يمكننا تجنب الشك
that in our case it's started to happen.
انه في حالتنا قد بدأت بالحدوث
We have got skin lined with this layer.
حيث ان الشحوم موجوده جنبا الى جنب مع جلدنا
It's the only possible explanation of why humans,
هذا التفسير الوحيد الذي بسببه الانسان
if they're very unlucky,
اذا كان حظه سيئاً جداً
can become grossly obese,
يمكن ان يصبح مفرط البدانة
in a way that would be totally impossible for any other primate, physically impossible.
بشكل سيكون من المستحيل تماما على الرئيسيات الأخرى ، جسديا المستحيل
Something very odd, matter-of-factly, never explained.
شيء غريب جدا, ولا يمكن تفسيره
The question of why we can speak.
السؤال الذي يقول لماذا نحن الوحيدين القادرين على الكلام
We can speak.
نحن نستطيع الكلام
And the gorilla can't speak. Why?
بينما الغوريلا لا تستطيع ذلك
Nothing to do with his teeth or his tongue or his lungs or anything like that --
لا شيء له علاقة بأسنانها او لسانها او رئتيها وغيرها
purely has to do with its conscious control of its breath.
لكن له علاقة بقدرته على التحكم الواعي بطريقة تنفسه
You can't even train a gorilla to say "Ah" on request.
حتى انه لا يمكنك تدريب غوريلا ان تقول "اّه" عند طلب ذلك
The only creatures that have got conscious control of their breath
المخلوقات الوحيدة التي لها القدرة على التحكم الواعي بالتنفس
are the diving animals and the diving birds.
الحيوانات الغواصة، و الطيور الغواصة
It was an absolute precondition for our being able to speak.
و ذلك شرط اساسي مسبق لقدرتنا على الكلام
And then again, there is the fact that we are streamlined.
و بعد ذلك حقيقة اننا انسيابي الشكل
Trying to imagine a diver
حاولو ان تتخيلو غواص بشري
diving into water -- hardly makes a splash.
يغطس في الماء، يكاد يحدث طرطشة
Try to imagine a gorilla
و الان حاول ان تتخيل غوريلا
performing the same maneuver,
تؤدي نفس المناورة
and you can see that, compared with gorilla,
و سترى انه و بالمقارنة مع الغوريلا
we are halfway to being shaped like a fish.
اننا اقرب الى شكل السمكة
I am trying to suggest that, for 40-odd years,
لقد كنت احاول قول ذلك منذ 40 عاما و نيف
this aquatic idea has been miscategorized as lunatic fringe,
هذه النظرية المائية قد صنفت خطأً على انها حافة الجنون
and it is not lunatic fringe.
و هي ليست كذلك
And the ironic thing about it is that
وما يثير للسخرية هو
they are not staving off the aquatic theory
انهم لم يبطلوا النظرية المائية
to protect a theory of their own,
ليحموا نظريتهم الخاصة
which they've all agreed on, and they love.
التي اتفقوا عليها جميعاً، و احبوها
There is nothing there.
ليس هنالك شيء
They are staving off the aquatic theory
انهم يبطلون النظرية المائية
to protect a vacuum.
ليحموا شيئاً فارغاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
How do they react when I say these things?
كيف ستكون ردة فعلهم عندما يسمعوني اقول هذه الاشياء
One very common reaction I've heard about 20 times
ردة فعل واحدة دائماً، سمعتها من 20 دقيقة
is, "But it was investigated.
وهي "لكن يتم التحقيق فيها
They conducted a serious investigation of this at the beginning,
لقد حققوا فيها تحقيقاً جاداً منذ البداية
when Hardy put forward his article."
عندما قدم هاردي مقالته"
I don't believe it.
انا لا اصدق ذلك
For 35 years I've been looking for any evidence
كنت ابحث من 35 عاماً على ادلة
of any incident of that kind,
على اية حادثة من هذا النوع
and I've concluded that that's one of the urban myths.
و قد توصلت الى ان واحدة من الاساطير الحضرية
It's never been done.
لم يحدث ذلك ابداً
I ask people sometimes, and they say,
انا اسال الناس احيانا، فيقولون
"I like the aquatic theory!
"لقد اعجبتني النظرية المائية!
Everybody likes the aquatic theory.
الجميع اعجبته النظرية المائية
Of course they don't believe it, but they like it."
طبعاً هم لم يصدقوها، ولكنها تعجبهم"
Well I say, "Why do you think it's rubbish?"
حسناً انا اقول "لماذا تعتبروها قمامة؟"
They say "Well ...
و هم يجاوبون " حسناً
everybody I talk to says it's rubbish.
كل شخص اكلمه عنها يقول انها قمامة
And they can't all be wrong, can they?"
و لا يمكن ان يكونوا جميعاً مخطئين، هل يمكن ذلك؟"
The answer to that, loud and clear, is, "Yes! They can all be wrong."
و الجواب على ذلك واضح و صريح،" نعم يمكن ان يكونوا جميعاً مخطئين"
History is strewn with the cases when they've all got it wrong.
يعج التاريخ بقضايا فهمناها جميعا بصورة خاطئة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And if you've got a scientific problem like that,
و اذا واجهتكم مشكلة علمية مثل هذه
you can't solve it by holding a head count,
لا يمكنكم مواجهتها عن طريق عقد لجنة
and saying, "More of us say yes than say no."
و القول " الموافقون اكثر من المعارضون"
(Laughter)
( ضحك)
Apart from that, some of the heads count more than others.
فضلاً عن ذلك، بعضهم اكثر من غيرهم
Some of them have come over.
بعضهم عليه ان يبدل رأيه
There was Professor Tobias. He's come over.
هناك البروفسور توبياس الذي غيّر رأيه
Daniel Dennett, he's come over.
دانيال دينيت غيّر رأيه
Sir David Attenborough, he's come over.
السيد ديفيد أتينبورو غيّر رأيه
Anybody else out there? Come on in.
هل هناك احد اخر؟ هيا تفضلوا
The water is lovely.
الماء جميل
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And now we've got to look to the future.
و الان علينا النظر الى المستقبل
Ultimately one of three things is going to happen.
بشكلٍ اكيد سيحدث واحدٌ من ثلاثة
Either they will go on for the next 40 years, 50 years, 60 years.
اما ان يتابعوا لل 40، 50، 60 عاماً القادمة
"Yeah well we don't talk about that. Let's talk about something interesting."
"حسناً لن نتحدث عن ذلك، لنتحدث عن شيء ممتع"
That would be very sad.
و ذلك سيكون مؤسفاً
The second thing that could happen
الامر الثاني الذي قد يحدث
is that some young genius will arrive,
قدوم شاب عبقري
and say, "I've found it.
و يقول" لقد وجدتها
It was not the savanna, it was not the water, it was this!"
انها ليست السافننا، و ليست الماء، انها هذا !"
No sign of that happening either.
و لا دليل على حدوث هذا ايضاً
I don't think there is a third option.
لا اظن ان هناك خيار ثالث
So the third thing that might happen is
اذا اعتقد ان الامر الثالث الذي قد يحدث هو
a very beautiful thing.
شيءٌ جميلٌ جداً
If you look back at the early years of the last century,
اذا نظرتم الى الاعوام الاولى من القرن السابق
there was a stand-off, a lot of bickering and bad feeling
كان هناك مواجهة، و الكثير من المشاحنات، و الشعور بالإستياء
between the believers in Mendel,
بين اتباع مندل
and the believers in Darwin.
و اتباع داروين
It ended with a new synthesis:
التي انتهت بتركيب جديد
Darwin's ideas and Mendel's ideas
افكار داروين، و افكار مندل
blending together.
مزجت سوياً
And I think the same thing will happen here.
و انا اعتقد ان ذلك سيحصل هنا
You'll get a new synthesis.
ستحصلون على تركيب جديد
Hardy's ideas and Darwin's ideas
افكار هاردي، و افكار داروين
will be blended together.
ستمزج سوياً
And we can move forward from there,
و يمكننا المتابعة من هناك
and really get somewhere.
و الوصول الى شيء حقيقي
That would be a beautiful thing.
و سيكون ذلك جميلاً
It would be very nice for me if it happened soon.
و سيكون جميلاً بالنسبة لي اذا حدث ذلك قريباً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Because I'm older now than George Burns was when he said,
لانني انا الان اكبر من جورج برنز عندما قال
"At my age, I don't even buy green bananas."
"بسنّي هذا، لا اشتري موزاً اخضر"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So if it's going to come and it's going to happen,
لذا ان كان ذلك اتٍ و سيحدث
what's holding it up?
ما الذي يمنعه
I can tell you that in three words.
استطيع قول ذلك بثلاثة كلمات
Academia says no.
الدوائر الاكادمية قالت لا
They decided in 1960,
لقد قرروا في عام 1960
"That belongs with the UFOs and the yetis."
"هذا يعود الى الاجسام الغريبة و الغيلان"
And it's not easy to change their minds.
و ليس من السهل اقناعهم بالعدول عن رأيهم
The professional journals
الصحفيون المحترفون
won't touch it with a barge pole.
لن يلمسوها بقطب البارجة
The textbooks don't mention it.
الكتاب لم يذكر ذلك
The syllabus doesn't mention even the fact that we're naked,
حتى المنهج لم يذكر حقيقة اننا عراة
let alone look for a reason to it.
ناهيك عن البحث عن اجابة لذلك
"Horizon," which takes its cue from the academics,
"الافق" التي تاخذ اشارتها من الاكادميين
won't touch it with a barge pole.
لن تلمسها بقطب البارجة
So we never hear the case put for it,
لكي لا نسمع عن القضية التي وضعت عنها
except in jocular references
الا عن طريق المزح
to people on the lunatic fringe.
للناس الذين هم على حافة الجنون
I don't know quite where this diktat comes from.
انا لا اعرف تماما من اين يأتي هذا الاملاء
Somebody up there
هناك احد ما في الاعلى
is issuing the commandment,
يصدر الاوامر
"Thou shalt not believe in the aquatic theory.
"يجب ان لا تصدقوا النظرية المائية"
And if you hope to make progress in this profession,
و اذا كنتم تأملون تحقيق النجاح في هذه المهنة
and you do believe it, you'd better keep it to yourself,
و انتم تصدقونها، عليكم ان تبقوها لنفسكم
because it will get in your way."
لانه ستقف في طريقك
So I get the impression that some parts
لذا حصلت على انطباع ان بعض اجزاء
of the scientific establishment
المؤسسة العلمية
are morphing into a kind of priesthood.
تتحول الى نوع من الكهنوت.
But you know, that makes me feel good,
و لكن تعلمون، هذا يشعرني بتحسن
because Richard Dawkins has told us
لان ريتشارد دوكينز قال لنا
how to treat a priesthood.
كيف نتعامل مع الكهنوت
(Laughter)
(تصفيق)
He says, "Firstly, you've got to refuse to give it
قال " اولاً يجب ان ترفض اعطاءها
all the excessive awe and reverence
الرهبة والخشوع المفرطة
it's been trained to receive."
لانها دُربت على تلقيها"
Right. I'll go ahead with that.
صحيح، و انا اوافق على ذلك
And secondly, he says,
و ثانياً قال
"You must never be afraid to rock the boat."
يجب ان لا تخاف ابداً من ان تهز القارب
I'll go along with that too.
و اوافق على هذا ايضاً
Thank you very much.
شكراً لكم جميعاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)